<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY date "August 2010">
  <!ENTITY version "0.5.0">
  <!ENTITY application "TFLA-01">
]>
<article id="index" lang="en">

  <!-- Header -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>The Fabulous Logic Analyzer #1</title>

    <pubdate>&date;</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
      <year>2006</year>
      <year>2007</year>
      <year>2008</year>
      <year>2009</year>
      <year>2010</year>
      <holder>Bernhard Walle</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
      <para>
        Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
        under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
        any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
        Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover
        Texts. The complete license text is available from the <ulink
        type="http" url="http://www.gnu.org/">Free Software Foundation</ulink>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <!-- <authorgroup> -->
      <author>
        <firstname>Bernhard</firstname>
        <surname>Walle</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <address><email>bernhard@bwalle.de</email></address>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    <!-- </authorgroup> -->

    <releaseinfo>
      This manual describes version &version; of &application;.
    </releaseinfo>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introduction to &application;</title>

    <sect2 id="whatislogicanalyzer">
      <title>What is a logic analyzer?</title>

      <para>
        A logic analyzer is a device which can monitor the high and low states of several
        input lines of a digital logic. It is useful for debugging digital circuits such
        as bus transfers, etc. You can imagine a logic analyzer to be something like
        a digital oscilloscope.
      </para>

      <para>
        Normally, a logic analyzer is a external device with a own controller that has a own
        display or is connected to a PC via USB or serial line. The PC or the display then
        shows the data, e. g. some waveforms.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="whatsspecial">
      <title>What's special about TFLA-01?</title>

      <para>
        This logic analyzer is designed to be cheap, somehing like a logic analyzer for poor
        men, which means not for industrial use but for hobbyists. It simply consits of a
        schematic which is attached to the PCs parallel port. Therefore, 8 Bit (i. e.
        8 data lines) can be monitored simultaneously.
      </para>

      <para>There's no real external device which
        collects the data: The schematic just protects the parallel port and converts RS232
        level (+/- 12 V) to 5 V TTL level on two pins configurable with jumpers.
        The schematic is described later in this manual. The measuring is done by the PC software
        using the parallel port.
      </para>

      <para>
        This means that the speed depends on your PCs parallel port and on the operating system.  The data ist just
        collected by a user process to be portable against different operating system. However, with my setup I get on
        Linux data rates about 1 MHz which is quite well for I²C, RS-232, SPI and some other stuff.
      </para>

      <para>The software has following features:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Triggering </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Zooming </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Two markers for which the (estimated) times are displayed </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Application runs completely in userspace,
            <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/libieee1284/">libieee1284</ulink> is used
            for parallel port access. This means that the installation is easy and the system
            stays stable.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Integrated decoder for the I²C and SPI protocols.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sysreqs">
      <title>System requirements</title>

      <para>
        TFLA-01 is designed to be portable against various operating systems. It is written
        in C++, uses <ulink url="http://www.trolltech.com/products/qt/">Qt</ulink> as
        cross-plattform API mostly for the graphical user interface and
        <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/libieee1284/">libieee1284</ulink> to access
        the parallel port. This means that it is possible to run TFLA-01 on following
        systems:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Linux</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Windows</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>OpenBSD (i386 only)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>FreeBSD /i386</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Solaris/x86</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        On hardware side, you need a parallel port. Use the port of your mainboard or a
        additional PCI card. Forget about USB adapters, they are normally designed for
        printers and for nothing else and if it would work, the speed would be insuitable for
        a logic analyzer. (Of course, USB is faster than a parallel port, but that does nothing
        say about the speed of such adapters.)
      </para>

      <para>
        Starting with version 0.3.0 it's also possible to create a viewer-only version of TFLA-01.
        This version doesn't need libieee1284 and cannot collect data from the parallel port. It
        just can open TFLA-01 files that have been saved by another version of TFLA-01 (with
        parallel port access).  If no libieee1284 is available, the build system warns about missing
        functionality but automatically builds such a version.  However, such binaries are not
        distributed at the <ulink url="http://tfla-01.berlios.de">TFLA-01 website</ulink>. This
        version also works on Mac OS.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="gettingstarted">
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <para>
      You should read this section if you would like to install TFLA-01 on your
      system and get it working. Don't ask me any questions per E-Mail if you didn't
      read this chapter of the documentation completely!
    </para>

    <sect2 id="installingsoftware">
      <title>Installing the software</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Primary installation</title>

        <sect4>
          <title>Linux packages</title>


          <para>
            Packages for openSUSE and SUSE Linux Enterprise 10 can be obtained
            in the
            <ulink
              url="http://software.opensuse.org/search?q=tfla-01&amp;baseproject=electronics">openSUSE
              BuildService</ulink>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Start the logic analyzer via command line by running

            <screen>$ tfla-01</screen>

            or add a shortcut to your desktop's start menu. In <filename>/usr/share/pixmaps</filename>
            you find some icons which you can use for that.
          </para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4>
          <title>Windows Binaries</title>

          <para>
            On the <ulink url="http://tfla-01.berlios.de">webpage</ulink>, the author provides
            binaries for TFLA-01 for (32 bit) Windows as a ZIP archive. Just extract that archive to
            some directory and you're done. Don't forget to install the <emphasis>giveio</emphasis>
            software as described in <xref linkend="winpermissions" endterm="winpermissionstitle" />.
            After that, just start TFLA-01 by double-clicking on the program icon.
          </para>

          <para>
            If the system complains about missing libraries, you have to install the
            <emphasis>Microsoft Visual C++ 2008 Redistributable Package</emphasis>.
            Just enter that term in a search engine of your choice and you'll find the download site
            at Microsoft. Since the links that Microsoft provides are not <quote>stable</quote>, I
            didn't want to include the direct link in that documentation. Ensure that the language
            is identical to your Windows installation, and then download and install that software.
            After that software is installed, try again.
          </para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4>
          <title>Unix via source code</title>

          <para>
            The normal way to install TFLA-01 on Unix is to compile the source code since
            it is impossible for me to provide binaries for all various plattforms. If you've built
            a binary (preferrable a package) for your favourite Unix flavour and you plan to maintain
            it for future TFLA-01 releases, just drop me a note and I'll put a link on the TFLA-01
            homepage or upload the binary. The users will thank you!
          </para>

          <para>
            However, compiling TFLA-01 is not difficult since the dependencies are small.
            Building on Microsoft Windows is different, so this chapter only describes the
            build procedure on Unix. At first, make sure that you have following software
            installed and that the preconditions are met:
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gcc">gcc</ulink> or another C++ compiler
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <ulink url="http://qt.nokia.com/products/">Qt</ulink> 4.5 including
                the developement package. Verify this by running <application>qmake</application>
                on command line.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/libieee1284/">libieee1284</ulink> including
                the developement package (which includes the header files).
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <ulink url="http://www.cmake.org/">CMake</ulink> to build the software.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org">Docbook</ulink> to build the documentation which is done during the
                build process.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>
            To make things easier, the following <link linkend="packagestable">table</link> shows the packages that you
            need to install on common Linux distributions. If your distribution is not listed and you know how to fill
            the table, don't hesitate to contact the <ulink url="mailto:bernhard@bwalle.de">author</ulink>.
          </para>

          <table frame='all' id="packagestable">
            <title>Dependency packages on different distributions</title>
            <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Distribution</entry>
                  <entry>Packages</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>openSUSE</entry>
                  <entry>
                    <literal>qt-devel</literal>
                    <literal>libieee1284</literal>
                    <literal>cmake</literal>
                    <literal>docbook-xsl-stylesheets</literal>
                    <literal>gcc-c++</literal>
                    <literal>libpng-devel</literal>
                    <literal>libpng</literal>
                    <literal>freetype2-devel</literal>
                    <literal>libxslt</literal>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Ubuntu</entry>
                  <entry>
                    <literal>cmake</literal>
                    <literal>g++</literal>
                    <literal>qtbase5-dev</literal>
                    <literal>qttools5-dev</literal>
                    <literal>libieee1284-3-dev</literal>
                    <literal>xsltproc</literal>
                    <literal>docbook-xml</literal>
                    <literal>docbook-xsl</literal>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Fedora</entry>
                  <entry>
                    <literal>cmake</literal>
                    <literal>gcc-c++</literal>
                    <literal>qt-devel</literal>
                    <literal>libxslt</literal>
                    <literal>docbook-style-xsl</literal>
                    <literal>libieee1284-devel</literal>
                  </entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>

          <para>
            Now after everything is right, just build the software now with following commands:
          </para>

          <screenco>

            <areaspec>
              <area id="unused" coords="1"/>
            </areaspec>

<screen>$ mkdir build    <co id="createdir" />
$ cd build
$ cmake ..       <co id="configure" />
$ make           <co id="make" />
</screen>

            <calloutlist>
              <callout arearefs="createdir">
                <para>
                  Since it's usual to build the binaries in another directory than the source
                  directory with CMake, we create a <filename>build</filename> directory first and
                  change into that. It would be possible to use another name or even another
                  location (not a subdirectory). however, using <filename>build</filename> is quite
                  common.
                </para>
              </callout>
              <callout arearefs="configure">
                <para>
                  With the call to <command>cmake</command>, the build system is configured.
                  Please refer to the documentation of CMake for advanced options. The most
                  important option is <option>-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX</option> which corresponds
                  to the well-known <option>--prefix</option> option when using
                  <command>./configure</command> scripts. Example:
                  <option>-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=/usr</option>. The default is
                  <filename>/usr/local</filename>.
                </para>
              </callout>
              <callout arearefs="make">
                <para>
                  Now after the <filename>Makefile</filename> is present, we can build the program.
                  You can use <literal>-j NUMBER_OF_JOBS</literal> to speed up things on multi-core
                  systems. However, since the program is quite small, it's probably not worth the
                  effort.
                </para>
              </callout>
            </calloutlist>
          </screenco>

          <para>
            To install the software, just run

            <screen>$ sudo make install</screen>
          </para>

          <para>
            That's it! Please don't forget to read the <xref linkend="permissions" endterm="permissionstitle" />
            section.
          </para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Windows via source code</title>

          <para>
            Using CMake, it's possible to build the program with Microsoft Visual Studio
            (the free <quote>Express Edition</quote>). The sources of the libieee1284 that
            are included in the TFLA-01 distribution can be used for that. That subdirectory
            includes an own <filename>CMakeLists.txt</filename> file that should be used to build
            the library. Then the library path for libieee1284 can be set to that subdirectory.
          </para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="permissions">
        <title>Permissions</title>
        <titleabbrev id="permissionstitle">Permissions</titleabbrev>

        <para>
          Because you want to run the application as normal user and not only as administrator,
          you have to deal with permissions of the operating system. This depends really on the
          system (i. e. there are differences between Unix flavours and even Windows versions)
          and does not depend whether you compile the program by hand or use a binary
          to install, so I made an extra section.
        </para>

        <sect4>
          <title>Linux</title>

          <para>
            On recent Linux versions (Kernel 2.4 and higher), the applications uses internally
            the <application>ppdev</application> kernel module. It should be loaded automatically.
            If not, use
          </para>

          <screen># modprobe ppdev </screen>

          <para>
            to load the module once. On SUSE, you can add the module to
            <literal>MODULES_LOADED_ON_BOOT</literal> variable in
            <filename>/etc/sysconfig/kernel</filename>. On Debian and Ubuntu, the string <literal>ppdev</literal>
            can be added to <filename>/etc/modules</filename> if the <application>ppdev</application> is not
            loaded automatically.
          </para>

          <para>
            The other thing you have to make sure is that the user which runs the TFLA-01
            program has read and write permissions to the <filename>/dev/paraportX</filename>
            device file where <literal>X</literal> means the number of the parallel port you
            want to access.
          </para>

          <para>
            On Ubuntu, the file <filename>/dev/paraportX</filename> is owned by the <literal>lp</literal> group.
            So all you have to do is to add your user to that group:
          </para>

          <screen># adduser USERNAME lp</screen>

          <para>
            Don't forget to re-login so that that change applies.
          </para>

          <para>
            If the device <filename>/dev/parportX</filename> is owned by <literal>root</literal>, the classical
            approach is to create a group <emphasis>parport</emphasis>, set
            the owning group of the parallel port device to <emphasis>parport</emphasis>, change
            the parallel port to <literal>crw-rw----</literal> and add the users to the group
            as necessary. Read the manual of your Linux distribution for details. Since the
            device files are normally created by <application>udev</application> in a modern
            distribution, you have to add a file
            <filename>/etc/udev/rules.d/90-parport.rules</filename> that
            contains
          </para>

<programlisting>
KERNEL="parport[0-9]", MODE="664", GROUP="parport"
</programlisting>

          <para>
            It's also possible to add this to an existing rules files, but
            that's problematic for updates. Creating a new file is the cleaner
            approach. The number determines the order in which the files are
            used -- for the parallel port, that doesn't matter.  Add all users
            that should have permission to use the parallel port to that group.
            You have to log out and log in again to apply this.
          </para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="winpermissions">
          <title>Windows 2000/XP</title>
          <titleabbrev id="winpermissionstitle">Windows 2000/XP permissions</titleabbrev>

          <para>
            If you want to run it in user mode you need to use the giveio driver that is supplied
            with <ulink url="http://savannah.nongnu.org/projects/avrdude/">avrdude</ulink>. The
            installation of giveio is described in the documentation of avrdude.
          </para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="buildhardware">
      <title>Building the hardware</title>

      <para>
        A schematic in <ulink url="http://www.cadsoft.de/">Eagle</ulink> and <abbrev>PDF</abbrev>
        format is distributed with the program. In source Tarball, you find the schematic
        in <filename>doc/schematic</filename> and it gets installed in
        <filename>PREFIX/share/doc/schematic</filename> on any plattform. You can also view
        it <ulink url="http://tfla-01.berlios.de/pics/schematic.png">online</ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>It should be easy for you to get and solder the components. The components are
        cheap and should be available at any electronic part store. In Germany, for example
        at <ulink url="http://www.reichelt.de">Reichelt</ulink> <footnote><para>No, I don't
        get any money from this company.</para></footnote>. If anything is unclear,
        feel free to send me an email at <email>bernhard@bwalle.de</email> and hope to get
        a reply. If anyone made a board layout (preferrable with
        <ulink url="http://www.cadsoft.de/">Eagle</ulink>, too) it would be nice if you could
        sent it to me so that I can it include in the TFLA-01 distribution or just link
        on the <ulink url="http://tfla-01.berlios.de">TFLA-01 homepage</ulink>.
      </para>

      <figure id="board">
        <title>Image of my hand-made Logic Analyzer</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata  fileref="images/board.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Image of my hand-made Logic Analyzer</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        To connect it to the parallel port of the PC, you have to solder a small adapter
        because of the different connectors. You can also use a SUB-D plug on the board and
        a standard cable.
      </para>

    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="tryitout">
      <title>Now try it out</title>

      <para>
        After you installed the program and built the hardware, it's time to test it.
        Insert a battery in the logic analyzer and power it on by connecting the
        <literal>JP-POWER</literal> jumper. A green LED should show that the power supply works.
        Now use a wire to connect pin 9 and 8 of the <literal>ANALYZE</literal> jack. Start
        the TFLA-01 application by typing <command>tfla-01</command> on Unix or by double-clicking
        the TFLA-01 icon in the Windows explorer.
      </para>

      <para>
        After the TFLA-01 window appears, choose a parallel port in the
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenu>Ports</guimenu></menuchoice> menu.
        All other default settings should work, so just click on the
        <guiicon>Start</guiicon> icon, use the <menuchoice><guimenu>Analyze</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Start</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu item or press
        <keycombo><keycap>F5</keycap></keycombo>. You should see something like the
        screenshot below:
      </para>

      <figure id="shot-getting-started">
        <title>Screenshot of the TFLA-01</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/shot-getting-started.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Image of my hand-made Logic Analyzer</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

      <para>
        Because there's no changing signal, you see nothing special. The pin 8 is connected
        to GND while all other pins are unused which means high level here. The grid on the
        screen represents the samples. Just before the line is drawn the application
        displays the number of collected samples in the status line. This may give you a
        hint how fast your parallel port is. You can work out the sample frequency now,
        it's <emphasis>1/(number of samples)</emphasis>.
      </para>

      <para>
        Congratulation, your logic analyzer is working. Play a bit now and come back to this
        documentation to discover all features of the software (which are, of couse, not very
        much).
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="hardwareconfig">
    <title>Hardware description and configuration</title>

    <sect2 id="connectors">
      <title>Connections</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>PARPORT</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Connect this to the PCs parallel port (IEEE 1284). You find the pin
              configuration of that port at
              <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_port#Pinouts"/>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>ANALYZE</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This connector is used to connect the 8 data lines to a schematic (e. g. a
              I²C bus or a RS-232 line). You have to connect <emphasis>GND</emphasis> and
              between one and eight data lines.
            </para>

            <para>
              The first two pins (number 1 and 2) can be connected to a 5 V logic (TTL level)
              or to a +/- 12 V (RS-232) logic depending on the jumper settings
              (see <link linkend="jumpers">Jumpers</link>). The other pins (3 to 8) can
              only be connected to a 5 V logic.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>9V-IN</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This is the power supply for the board. We use an external power supply instead of
              using a pin of the parallel port because the parallel port is not designed to
              provide current for devices and this solution only may work with the
              <emphasis>74HC245N</emphasis> IC but not with the <emphasis>MAX232</emphasis>.
            </para>

            <para>
              Connect this to a 9 V battery or power supply unit. The 9 V are not critical,
              you can also use 12 V. Refer to the datasheet of the <emphasis>7805</emphasis> IC
              for the accurate range.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="jumpers">
      <title>Jumpers</title>

      <para>
        The hardware (as described in <link linkend="buildhardware">Building the hardware</link>)
        has follwing jumpers:
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>JP-POWER</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para> Use this jumper to power-off or power-on the circuit. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>JP-SER-1-DIS</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If this jumper is connected, the input pin 1 can be used as 5 V input. If it is
              disconnected, it may be used for +/- 12 V. Important: If
              <emphasis>JP-SER-1-DIS</emphasis> is connected, <emphasis>JS-SER1-EN1</emphasis> and
              <emphasis>JS-SER1-EN2</emphasis> must be disconnected.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>JS-SER1-EN1</emphasis> and <emphasis>JS-SER1-EN2</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If these jumpers are connected, the input pin 1 can be used as +/- 12 V input.
              If they are disconnected, it may be used for 5 V. Important: If
              <emphasis>JS-SER1-EN1</emphasis> and <emphasis>JS-SER1-EN2</emphasis>
              are connected, <emphasis>JP-SER-1-DIS</emphasis> must be disconnected.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>JP-SER-2-DIS</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If this jumper is connected, the input pin 2 can be used as 5 V input. If it is
              disconnected, it may be used for +/- 12 V. Important: If
              <emphasis>JP-SER-2-DIS</emphasis> is connected, <emphasis>JS-SER2-EN1</emphasis> and
              <emphasis>JS-SER2-EN2</emphasis> must be disconnected.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>JS-SER2-EN1</emphasis> and <emphasis>JS-SER2-EN2</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If these jumpers are connected, the input pin 2 can be used as +/- 12 V input.
              If they are disconnected, it may be used for 5 V. Important: If
              <emphasis>JS-SER2-EN1</emphasis> and <emphasis>JS-SER2-EN2</emphasis>
              are connected, <emphasis>JP-SER-2-DIS</emphasis> must be disconnected.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="leds">
      <title>LEDs</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis>LED-POWER</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If the LED lights, the circuit is connected with power.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="extendedusage">
    <title>Extended usage</title>

    <sect2 id="navigation">
      <title>Navigation</title>

      <para>
        Navigation is important for the plot area (that's the area where the data graph
        is displayed). There are several possible ways of navigation:
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Keyboard navigation</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Use the <keycap>Left</keycap> and <keycap>Right</keycap> cursor keys for slow
              navigation and the <keycap>Page Up</keycap> and <keycap>Page Down</keycap> key
              for fast navigation. Use <keycap>Home</keycap> and <keycap>End</keycap> to
              get to the start or to the end of the display area.
            </para>
            <para>
              To support <link linkend="markers">markers</link>, the <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Left</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Right</keycap></keycombo> shortcut can be used to jump to the left
              or right marker.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Toolbar</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The toolbar also has items for navigation: Use the <guiicon>Left</guiicon>
              and <guiicon>Right</guiicon> icon to navigate slow, the <guiicon>Page left</guiicon>
              and <guiicon>Page right</guiicon> icon to navigate fast and the
              <guiicon>Begin</guiicon> and <guiicon>End</guiicon> icon to navigate to the
              top or bottom of the data area.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Scrollbar</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You should be familar how to use a scrollbar. However, note that while dragging
              the slider the display is not updated. This is because of performance reasons
              if the displayed area is large.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Mouse wheel</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If you have a wheel mouse, it's very easy to navigate. Just rotate the mouse
              wheel to move forward/backward in the timeline or press the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              key while roatating to move faster.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Menu entries</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The <guimenu>Navigation</guimenu> menu holds the whole functions as menu items.
              This items are not intended to used by choose them from the menu but they are
              provided to present the keyboard shortcuts in a common way to the user.
            </para>
            <para>
              Only the <guimenuitem>Jump to left marker</guimenuitem> and
              <guimenuitem>Jump to right marker</guimenuitem> items may be accessed directly.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zooming">
      <title>Zooming</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Keyboard zooming</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Use <keycap>+</keycap> to zoom in, <keycap>-</keycap> to zoom out,
              <keycap>F2</keycap> to come back to the default zoom factor,
              <keycap>F3</keycap> to fit the whole data on the display and
              <keycap>F4</keycap> to fit the marked data (markers are discussed later)
              on the screen.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Toolbar</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Use <guiicon>Zoom In</guiicon> to zoom in, <guiicon>Zoom Out</guiicon> to zoom out,
              <guiicon>Zoom Default</guiicon> to come back to the default zoom factor,
              <guiicon>Zoom Fit</guiicon> to fit the whole data on the display and
              <guiicon>Zoom to fit markers</guiicon> to fit the marked data (markers are
              discussed later) on the screen.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Mouse wheel</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If you hold the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while rotating the mouse wheel,
              scrolling is performed. For other scrolling actions use the toolbar, the
              keyboard or the menu entries.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Menu entries</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu holds the whole functions as menu items.
              This items are not intended to used by choose them from the menu but they are
              provided to present the keyboard shortcuts in a common way to the user.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="markers">
      <title>Markers</title>

      <para>
        Markers (TFLA-01 provides two of them) are useful in much situations:

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              To show the (mostly) exact time of a certain point in the plot area. The
              time cannot be exact because we don't use realtime capabilities of the operating
              system (neither "normal" Linux now Windows have hard realtime capabilities) but
              it is accurate enough in most situations.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              To show a time difference between two measuring points.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              To remember a position in the data area while scrolling to another position
              for a short while.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              To help for zooming: Just select the area you want to see more detailled and
              press <keycap>F4</keycap> or use the <guiicon>Zoom to fit markers</guiicon>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <figure id="shot-markers">
        <title>Screenshot of the TFLA-01 showing the use of markers</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/shot-markers.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Screenshot of the TFLA-01 showing the use of markers</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

      <para>
        TFLA-01 supports a so-called <emphasis>left marker</emphasis> and a
        <emphasis>right marker</emphasis>. To set markers, click on the plot area
        with the left or the right mouse button. The left marker is intended to be left
        of the right marker, but it must not. If not, the time difference is negative.
        See <link linkend="navigation">Navigation</link> to see how markers can be
        used to navigate and <link linkend="zooming">Zooming</link> for information
        about scrolling and markers.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="triggering">
      <title>Triggering</title>

      <para>
        Triggering is useful if you want to monitor a line for a longer period of time and
        you mostly wait for an event to occure. For example you are alone and you have to start
        the logic analyzer to monitor data and you also have to do some manual steps to start
        the action on the data lines to occure.
      </para>

      <para>
        For each line you can configure if the line should be low or high to trigger of if the line
        should be ignored. If all lines are set to <emphasis>ignore</emphasis>, triggering is
        disabled. The display of the three states may depend of the GUI style of <ulink
          url="http://www.trolltech.com/products/qt">Qt</ulink>, the screenshot shows the
        Cleanlooks, Motif/CDE, Plastique and Windows style. The first line is set to trigger on low
        level, the second on high level and all other lines are ignored.
      </para>

      <figure id="shot-triggering">
        <title>Triggering selection in different GUI styles</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/shot-triggering.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Triggering selection in different GUI styles</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

      <note>
        <para>
          Triggering may not work if the period where the value which should be triggered
          for is two low. Since the function which waits for the triggered data is a part of the
          <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/libieee1284/">libieee1284</ulink> parallel port
          library, we have no influence on this.
        </para>
        <para>
          Also, triggering may be implemented differently on the operating system. For
          example on Linux it's part of the kernel module which means that there's no
          CPU usage until the triggered value is detected.
        </para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="datameasuringsettings">
      <title>Data measuring settings</title>

      <sect3 id="time">
        <title>Measuring time</title>

        <para>The measuring time sets the time to sample data after the user clicked on
          <guiicon>Start</guiicon> and if he doesn't <guiicon>Stop</guiicon>. Note that depending
          on the system speed the quantity of data is large so the same is for the
          memory consumtion (expect 1 MByte per second). Also the GUI is slow if drawing
          large data areas in this situation.
          So normally, a timespan between 1 and 10 seconds is a good idea.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="samplerate">
        <title>Sample rate</title>

        <para>By default, TFLA-01 collects data with full sample rate. The sample rate
          may be reduced to get less data which makes larger timespans possible. The most
          right position of the slider means maximal sample rate.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="save_and_load">
      <title>Open and save</title>

      <para>
        It's possible to save the data that has been collected with TFLA-01 in an
        application-specific, binary format that can be opened with TFLA-01 again.
        The format is platform an machine independent, so a file that has been saved
        on a SPARC Solaris machine can be read on a Intel Windows machine and vice versa.
      </para>
      <para>
        To save the data, use <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Save
            data...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The default extension is <emphasis>dat</emphasis>.  To
        read the file again, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Open data...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. To open the last file after the application
        has been restarted, you can also use <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Open
            recent</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="save_plot">
      <title>Save plot image</title>

      <para>The current plot can be saved as image with
        <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Save current plot</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>. Currently, exaclty the displayed area is saved including the markers
        and the only supported format is PNG. This may change in future.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="export">
      <title>Export data</title>

      <para>The current data can be exported as CSV (comma separated value) with
        <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Export data...</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>. Each sample is a line and each bit is a column. This can
        be used with in a spreadsheet application like OpenOffice.org or in custom
        scripts.
      </para>
      <para>After the file has been selected, you will be asked if only the state changes should be
        saved. If you choose <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>, then only the data sets will be saved where
        something changed.  This reduces the file size dramatically.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="protocol-analyzers">
      <title>Bus protocol analyzers</title>

      <para>
        Starting with version 0.3.0, a tiny I²C analyzer has been integrated. This is a contribution by Jose Aparicio
        (<email>aparicio@lip.pt</email>). And with 0.4.0, even an analyzer for SPI has been integrated which has been
        contribued by Kai Dorau (<email>kai.dorau@gmx.net</email>). Both analyzers share a common user interface which
        is explained below.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="proto-assign-channel">
        <title>Assigning the input channels</title>

        <para>
          At first you have to tell the software which of your input channel represents which logic channel of the bus
          protocol. While I²C has the two lines <emphasis>SDA</emphasis> and <emphasis>SCL</emphasis> (data and clock),
          SPI has <emphasis>SDI</emphasis> (MOSI), <emphasis>SDO</emphasis> (MOSI) and <emphasis>SCK</emphasis>
          (data in, data out and clock). The SPI decoder supports only one data direction at a given time.
        </para>

        <para>
          To do the assignment, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Protocols</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Assign
              channels</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Then a dialog as shown below should appear.
        </para>

        <figure id="shot-channel-assignment">
          <title>Channel assignemt dialog</title>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/shot-channel-assignment.png" format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>
                <phrase>Channel assignemt dialog</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>
          In this dialog, it's possible to assign a protocol channel for each input channel.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="proto-decoding">
        <title>Doing the decoding</title>

        <para>
          If all protocol channels of a given protocol have been assigned, the corresponding entry in the
          <guimenu>Protocols</guimenu> menu should be enabled. To do the actual decoding, just select
          <menuchoice><guimenu>Protocols</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Analyze I²C</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
          or <menuchoice><guimenu>Protocols</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Analyze SPI</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
          After a short while, the result should be displayed in a dialog as shown below:
        </para>

        <figure id="shot-spi-analysis">
          <title>Result of a SPI protocol analysis</title>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/shot-spi-analysis.png" format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>
                <phrase>Result of a SPI protocol analysis</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>
          Just choose <guibutton>Save to file...</guibutton> to save the contents of that result dialog to a file.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>
            If you don't want to analyze the whole data set, just use the markers to select a start and end
            position. In that case, only the selected data set will be analyzed.
          </para>
        </note>

      </sect3>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="settings">
    <title>Settings</title>

    <para>TFLA-01 has a <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> menu where some configuration settings
      can be changed. The settings are stored permanently without user invocation. The
      data storage depends on the operating system: While on Unix the settings are stored
      in a configuration file (<filename>$HOME/.qt/tfla-01rc</filename>), the registry
      is used on Windows.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="colorsettings">
      <title>Color settings</title>
      <para>
        <guimenuitem>Change foreground color</guimenuitem> changes the color of the drawing
        line of the data plot. Note that the background is always black.
      </para>

      <para>
        <guimenuitem>Change color of left marker</guimenuitem> and
        <guimenuitem>Change color of right marker</guimenuitem> changes the color
        of the left marker (set with the left mouse button) and the right marker
        (right mouse button), respectively.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="parport">
      <title>Parallel port</title>

      <para>
        The parallel port can be configured in <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
        <guimenu>Port</guimenu></menuchoice>. Each detected port is displayed here.
        The detection is done only on startup, "hot plugging" is not supported (I even
        don't know hot-pluggable parallel ports).
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="aboutapplication">
    <title>About &application;</title>

    <sect2 id="copyright">
      <title>Copyright</title>

    <para>
        &application; and this documentation was written by Bernhard Walle
        (<email>bernhard@bwalle.de</email>). Visit the
        <ulink url="http://tfla-01.berlios.de" type="http">TFLA-01 website</ulink>
        for more information.
      </para>

      <para>
        This software is distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License
        as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
        (at your option) any later version.
      </para>

      <para>
        You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
        along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
        Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307,
        USA.
      </para>

      <para>
        This documentation can considered as part of the software and therefore has the same license
        and copyright conditions.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="credits">
      <title>Credits</title>

      <para>
        Stefan Holzer (<email>stefan-holzer@gmx.de</email>) provided Windows binaries
        in the past.
      </para>

      <para>
        Jose Aparicio (<email>aparicio@lip.pt</email>) contributed the I²C analyzer
        feature and parts of the data save/open feature.
      </para>

      <para>
        Kai Dorau (<email>kai.dorau@gmx.net</email>) contributed the SPI analyzer
        feature.
      </para>

      <para>
        The schematic was heavily inspired by
        <ulink url="http://www.xs4all.nl/~jwasys/old/diy2.html">JWA Systems -
        A logic analyzer using the PC's parallel port</ulink>. Without this website,
        this TFLA-01 probably would never have been created.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

</article>
<!-- vim:set ts=2 sw=2 et ai tw=120: :tabSize=2:indentSize=2:noTabs=true:maxLineLen=120:wordWrap=hard: -->
